Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Mine Workers of America PE.010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Mine Workers of America
1903-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.010
2.5 Linear Feet In 2 record cartons and 2 shared boxes
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Mine Workers of America (1903-1995) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. Founded in 1890, the United Mine Workers of America (UMWA) was and continues to be a leader in the labor movement in the United States, fighting for safe working conditions and good wages. Material in the collection ranges in date from the early 20th century through the present and consists of agreements, contracts, constitutions, and reports as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, leaflets, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Mine Workers of America (1903-1995) consists of agreements, constitutions, reports, hearings and statements, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications, ranging in date from 1903 to the present. Included are industry wide national agreements on wages for anthracite and bituminous coal workers as well as transcriptions from hearings and statements from the United States Anthracite Commission and the United States Coal Commission, dating from 1920. On a range of issues from democratic elections to health and safety, the collection contains printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications. As a significant contribution to organized labor, the UMWA created the Welfare and Retirement Fund in 1946. Annual reports from the Fund are represented in the collection from 1950-1989.
Historical Note
The United Mine Workers of America (UMWA) formed in 1890 with the merger of the Knights of Labor Trade Assembly No. 135 and the National Progressive Union of Miners and Mine Laborers. A leader in civil rights, the UMWA barred discrimination based on race, religion or national origin in its first constitution. The UMWA was a member of the American Federation of Labor and a driving force in the creation of the Congress of Industrial Organizations. John L. Lewis served as president from 1920-1960. The UMWA, under his charge, created the Welfare and Retirement Fund in contract with the United States government, which permanently changed the way that health care is delivered to workers in the coal industry. In 1989, members of the UMWA in West Virginia, Virginia and Kentucky went on strike against the Pittston Coal Company, the strike lasted for several months and was greeted with wide-ranging community and union support. Today, the UMWA continues to fight for safe working conditions, good wages, benefits and fair representation.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Contracts; Fliers (printed matter); Pamphlets.; Agreements.; Constitutions.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Publications (documents); Labor unions -- United States.; Press releases.; Labor unions; United Mine Workers of America
- Agreements and Contracts, 1971-1975 (Box 1)
- Agreements and Contracts, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
- Annual Calendars, 1976-1977, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
- Centennial Conference, 1990 (Box 1)
- Black Lung Association, circa 1969 (Box 1)
- Conditions in the Paint Creek District, West Virginia: Hearings, undated (Box 1)
- Constitutional Conventions, 1930, 1940 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1934-1956 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1960-1983 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 10)
- District 2, 1921, undated (Box 1)
- District 12, 1928 (Box 1)
- District 21, 1904, 1922 (Box 1)
- District 25, 1903 (Box 1)
- District 30, 1973 (Box 1)
- District 50, 1938-1968, undated (Box 1)
- Fliers, 1936-1993, undated (Box 1)
- Lawson, John R. Case (District 15), 1915 (Box 1)
- Local 13212 (Brotherhood of Marine Officers), 1958 (Box 1)
- Miners Committee for Boyle-Titler-Owens, undated (Box 1)
- Miners for Democracy, 1972-1973, undated (Box 1)
- National Labor Conference on Safe Energy and Full Employment, 1980 (Box 1)
- National Save the Miners Conference, 1928 (Box 1)
- Nationalization Research Committee, 1922 (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles on, 1974-1995, undated (Box 1)
- Press Releases, 1922 (Box 1)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1920-1980s, undated (Box 1)
- Pittston Company, Strike at, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
- Pittston Company, Strike at: Newspaper Clippings on, 1989 (Box 1)
- Posters, circa 1990s (Box Shared Tamiment XOS002)
- Publications Relating to, 1972-1990, undated (Box 1)
- United States Anthracite Commission: Statements (I), 1920 (Box 1)
- United States Anthracite Commission: Statements (II), 1920 (Box 2)
- United States Coal Commission: Briefs and Statements, 1923 (Box 2)
- Welfare and Retirement Fund, 1950-1954, undated (Box 2)
- Welfare and Retirement Fund, 1955-1959 (Box 2)
- Welfare and Retirement Fund, 1960-1969 (Box 2)
- Welfare and Retirement Fund, 1970-1979 (Box 2)
- Welfare and Retirement Fund, 1980-1989 (Box 2)